Robert Hare Papers 1764-1859 Mss.B.H22
American Philosophical Society
Robert Hare papers, 1764-1858
Mss.B.H22
American Philosophical Society
3.0 Linear feet
Personal and professional correspondence of the chemist Robert Hare, including drafts of letters to editors of journals on such varied topics as fish guano, slaughterhouses, paper money, and the meaning of the term "Yankee annexations." The collection originally contained over 300 scrolls, since disbound, which contained drafts of letters, essays, and lectures, composed by Hare on ordinary sheets of paper, then pasted end to end, and rolled up. The essay and lecture topics include: chemistry, storms, slavery, currency, fire-fighting, capital punishment, railroads, the Smithsonian Institution, Michael Faraday, religion and Spiritualism, riots in Philadelphia, epidemics, underwater blasting, and Ralph W. Emerson; there is some verse. The collection also contains an account book of Hare and his wife, 1806-1829 (180 pp.; B/H22#3); a volume by Hare on Cyclones (tornadoes), n.d. (ca. 60 pp.; B/H22#4); and Samuel Powel, Jr.'s "Short notes on a course of antiquities at Rome... under M. Byre Antiquarian," 1764. (60 pp.).
Hare, Robert, 1781-1858
Scope and Contents note
Series I Correspondence, 1764-1858 (6 boxes, 1.5 linear feet)
Series II Scrolls, ca.1845-1858 (6 boxes, 1.5 linear feet)
Bibliography
Edgar Fahs Smith, The Life of Robert Hare: an American Chemist (Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1917). Call no.: B H22s
African American History Note
In a series of essays originally rolled up as scrolls (Series II), Hare asserted that slavery was a positive good for slave, master, and community alike, but argued nevertheless that it be abolished gradually, with full compensation to slave owners, in favor of a free labor system marked by a pronounced racial subordination.
Naval History Note
The Hare Papers contain a few items which may be of interest to naval historians:
Maury, Matthew Fontaine, 1806-1873.
Maury, Matthew Fontaine. Letter to Robert Hare. 1852 January 17. Meteorological questions. 2 pages.
Henry, Joseph. Letter to Robert Hare. 1857 February 3. Concerning Matthew Fontaine Maury and his work on the seas. 2 pages.
United States. Navy.
United States, Department of the Navy. Letter to Robert Hare. 1850 February 14. Manuscript returned in error. 1 page.
Early American History Note
The Robert Hare collection is a large, diverse, and rich collection. The collection contains essays, lectures, and letters to and from Robert Hare, the preeminent chemist in the United States during much of the nineteenth century. But as this collection shows, Hare was far more than a chemist. His essays and lectures touch on an array of topics, including discussions of democracy, currency, history, slavery, among others. The APS collection captures the sophistication of Hare’s thought.
Summary(s) of Collection: The Robert Hare Collection is divided into two sections: correspondence and scrolls. The correspondence is primarily a record of Robert Hare’s ingoing and outgoing communications from the nineteenth century, but there is also a significant collection of letters from the 1790s from John Innes Clark, Robert Hare’s father-in-law, who was a merchant in Rhode Island, and a journal of a trip to Rome made in 1764 and written by an unknown author (possibly Samuel Powel Jr.).
Robert Hare’s correspondence touches on matters political, personal, financial, and scientific. There is little correspondence from Hare’s early adulthood, when he worked variously in his father’s brewery and in Rhode Island as a druggist. Among the earliest documents relating to Hare are two petitions from “the young citizens of Philadelphia of the District of Southwark and Northern Liberties” in 1798 that supported the Adams administration and that Hare was likely involved in organizing (one mentions Charles Hare) and commentary on Jefferson’s election in 1800. The correspondence picks up in the 1820s as Hare began to establish himself in the field of chemistry as a professor. The later correspondence often covers his involvement spiritualism.
The scrolls, so named because the Hare combined and rolled up individual lectures, reflect Hare’s intellectual and scientific interests. The topics covered in this section are extraordinarily wide ranging. Hare wrote on politics, war, religion, slavery, crime and punishment, railroads, chemistry, meteorology, literature, currency, and science. Such a range of interests reflect the civic activity of an intelligent, prominent, and wealthy reformer in the early republic. Hare’s political speeches are often biting and caustic attacks on Jeffersonians and Democrats. In many of these speeches Hare offers his own interpretation of American political history, which reflects Hare’s Federalist and Whiggish political outlook.
Finally, the collection includes a personal account book kept by Hare and his wife from 1806-1829. The account book lists the names of those with whom they have conducted business and the records can lend insight into their private consumption and tastes.
Related Archival Materials note
The Hare-Willing Papers (Mss.Ms.Coll.104) contain the correspondence of Hare's family and descendants, including some of notebooks of Hare's and additional correspondence. Hare appears as a correspondent in several other collections, including the Joseph Henry Letters (Mss.Ms.H39p), the Scientists Collection (Mss.509.L56), the C. L. Bonaparte Letters (Mss.B.B642.1.7), and the John Torrey Papers (Mss.B.T63.1).
The Printed Materials Department contains over 100 publications of Hare's from all periods of his career.
The Department of Rare Books and Manuscripts at the University of Pennsylvania Library contains miscellaneous materials from Hare (see Ms. Coll. 74), along with a thorough collection of his printed works.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired 1961, 1975, 1980.
Biographical/Historical note
Robert Hare (1781-1858, APS 1803) was a chemist best known as an experimentalist and an innovator in the production of chemical apparatus. His inventions include the calorimeter, the deflagrator, and, most significantly, the oxyhydrogen blowtorch. He was Professor of Chemistry at the University of Pennsylvania for nearly three decades. Toward the end of his life Hare was an outspoken supporter of Spiritualism.
Robert Hare recalled being dandled on the knee of George Washington, an event that seems to have remained in his mind as he grew older, tying him to the fate of his nation and to his position on the privileged end of the social hierarchy. Hare was born in Philadelphia in 1781, the son of Robert Hare, Sr., a major Philadelphia brewer, and Margaret Willing niece, of Thomas Willing, the political leader and president of the Bank of North America.
Hare evidently demonstrated an interest in chemistry from an early age. As a young man, he attended the Academy of the University of Pennsylvania. Possessed of an innate mechanical aptitude, Hare developed a passion for chemistry while attending the lectures of James Woodhouse (1770-1809, APS 1796), and in later years the pairing of instrumental and intellectual prowess made him one of the foremost chemical experimentalists and technical innovators in the nation. Hare was a junior member of the Philadelphia Chemical Society, where his associates and teachers, in addition to Woodhouse, were Joseph Priestley (1733-1804, APS 1785) and the mineralogist Adam Seybert (1773-1825, APS 1797).
Before he turned 20, Hare had begun to experiment toward a method of generating higher temperatures than possible in contemporary furnaces, adapting a keg from his father's brewery to develop an instrument he called the hydrostatic blow-pipe - the oxyhydrogen blowtorch. The blow-pipe proved invaluable in fusing previously infusable metals such as platinum, and, when used by Thomas Drummond to ignite calcium hydroxide, it was found to produce a remarkably bright light that became the preferred medium for lighthouses and the stage, called limelight. The small pamphlet that Hare wrote to describe his invention, Memoir on the Supply and Application of the Blow-Pipe... (1802), brought him international renown when it was republished in the prestigious English Philosophical Magazine and the French Annales de Chimie. He also described his findings in the annual address to the Chemical Society in 1801. Largely on the strength of this single invention, Hare was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1803 and was awarded an honorary medical degree by Yale in 1806. The discovery subsequently made him the first recipient of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences’ Rumford Medal in 1839.
Still barely in his majority, Hare continued to work for his father's brewery, devising new, tighter kegs and a modified stop cock. In 1802 he made the acquaintance Benjamin Silliman (1779-1864, APS 1805), Professor of Chemistry and Natural Philosophy at Yale, who had come to Philadelphia to hear the lectures of Woodhouse, Benjamin Smith Barton (1766-1815, APS 1759), and Caspar Wistar (1761-1818, APS 1787). Hare and Silliman conducted scientific experiments during this and subsequent visits by Silliman; they remained lifelong friends and correspondents.
In 1809, the availability of the chair in chemistry at the University of Pennsylvania vacated by the death of Joseph Woodward opened an opportunity for Hare to turn his full attention to the subject he loved. After he was denied the appointment for lack of a medical degree, Benjamin Rush (1745-1813, APS 1768) intervened to persuade the trustees to create a new position in the Medical School in Natural Philosophy. In 1810 Hare accepted the position, but since his course was listed only as an elective, he had few matriculants, and resigned two years later due to the lack of remuneration.
In 1811 Hare married Harriet Clark, daughter of the merchant John Innes Clark and his wife Lydia Bowen.
Hare returned to his father's brewery, where he entered into a bleak period. Assuming full managerial responsibilities for the brewery following his father's death, Hare ran into financial ruin during the economic chaos of the War of 1812. His efforts to make a living at selling gases and running a druggist's concern in Providence, Rhode Island (where his wife's family resided), were unavailing. His fortunes changed in 1818, when the College of William and Mary offered him a position as Professor of Natural Philosophy and later that same year, when the Medical School at University of Pennsylvania appointed him as Professor of Chemistry. He returned to Philadelphia and remained at the University of Pennsylvania for almost thirty years. Among the many students he worked with Hare during this period were Samuel H. Stout (1822-1903) and Joseph Leidy (1823-1891, APS 1849).
As an instructor, Hare was at his best with advanced students but was generally appreciated for his dramatic demonstrations of chemical principles, often employing apparatus he had developed himself. His Compendium of the Course of Chemical Instruction (1828) went through at least four editions before 1840, and is considered one of the most thorough chemical textbooks in antebellum America. Although he taught chemistry to a large number of medical students, his greatest contributions to his field were as an experimentalist and an innovator in the production of chemical apparatus. Among his most important inventions were the calorimeter (1819), the deflagrator (1821) for producing powerful electrical currents, the litrameter for measuring the specific gravity of fluids, a hydrostatic balance, a cryophorus, and a gas density balance. He was also responsible for isolating elemental boron and silicon, becoming the first American to produce metallic calcium, and was an active researcher in electrical theory and the devising of electrical apparatus. He donated his equipment to the fledgling Smithsonian Institution in 1849, only to have them destroyed by fire years later.
Hare, however, was never only a chemist. He wrote poetry and fiction, including Standish the Puritan (1850), and Overling; or, The Heir of Wycherly (1852), and was a diehard, politically conservative controversialist, describing himself as a "Washington Federalist" well into the 1850s. Beginning with his Defence of the American Character, or, An Essay on Wealth as an Object of Cupidity or the Means of Distinction in the United States (1819), a work that first appeared in the Federalist Port Folio, Hare wrote frequently on banking, finance, currency, tariff, and social order, almost always assailing those principles he identified as "Jeffersonian" or as leading to social-leveling.
Hare was not loath to participate in discussions of the major social issues of his day, including the abolition of slavery and the clash between capital and labor. A firm believer in social hierarchy, he considered himself an antislavery man, though advocating that freed slaves be relegated to a circumscribed subordinate status in American society and compensating slave owners for any losses they incurred. Importing freedmen to the north, he reasoned, would be beneficial to the former slaves - enabling them to be in closer contact with greater numbers of whites - but also financially beneficial to the northern community as a steady supply of cheap labor. A fear of servile insurrection - creating the grounds for another Haiti - led him to adopt an authoritarian stance toward his social inferiors.
Never backing away from scientific controversy, Hare waded into meteorology with an argument that tornadoes were the product of electrical currents in the atmosphere. Most famously, however, in 1854, he took on the task of testing Michael Faraday's theory that Spiritualist table-tilting was the product of involuntary muscular actions. Ever an ingenious mechanic, Hare developed an apparatus he called the Spiritoscope, designed to detect mediumistic fraud, and in the process of testing his machine, he became a Spiritualist convert. His undeniable scientific credentials made him a particularly fortunate believer for the movement, and with the publication of his book, Experimental Investigation of the Spirit Manifestations... (1855), Hare became one of the best known Spiritualists in the nation. Concomitantly, he drew the full wrath of the movement's adversaries. After a public lecture defending Spiritualist investigation before the American Association for the Advancement of Science, he drew calls for his expulsion from the organization, which appear only to have caused Hare to become more retrenchant in his views. However, never an orthodox religionist, his apparent agnosticism or atheism proved as unpalatable to Spiritualists as it did to non-Spiritualists. Nevertheless, he went to his grave with a firm belief that his device could “facilitate intercourse between spirits and mortals.”
Hare was a member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, and the American Philosophical Society. He was also an honorary member of the Smithsonian Institution. He died unexpectedly in Philadelphia in May, 1858, leaving behind his wife, Harriet Clark, and six children.
Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Bache, Franklin, 1792-1864; Channing, William Ellery, 1780-1842; Dunglison, Robley, 1798-1869; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867; Fisher, John, 1806-1882; Fisher, Richard; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878; Kane, John K., (John Kintzing), 1795-1858; Kirkbride, Thomas Story, 1809-1883; Maury, Matthew Fontaine, 1806-1873; Partridge, Charles; Powel, Samuel, Jr.; Silliman, Benjamin, Jr., 1816-1885; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864; Vaughan, Petty, 1788-1854; Vaughan, William, 1752-1850; Abolition, emancipation, freedom; African American; American Philosophical Society; Antebellum Politics; Antislavery movements--Pennsylvania; Banks and banking -- United States.; Blasting, Submarine; Blowpipe.; Business and Skilled Trades; Business Records and Accounts; Capital punishment.; Chemical apparatus; Chemistry; Chemists--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Cyclones.; Early National Politics; Education; Educational Material; Electricity--19th century; Epidemics--United States; Essays.; Federalist Party--Pennsylvania; Fire extinction; General Correspondence; Guano; Lectures; Literature; Literature, Arts, and Culture; Manuscript Essays; Mesmerism; Money; Paper money--United States--19th century; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Politics and government--19th century; Poems; Race, race relations, racism; Railroads; Religion; Rome (Italy)--Antiquities; Science and technology; Scientific Data; Sketchbooks; Slaughtering and slaughter-houses--United States--19th century; Slavery -- Pennsylvania.; Slaves, slavery, slave trade; Smithsonian Institution; Spiritualism--Pennsylvania; Storms; Tornadoes; Travel Narratives and Journals; United States--Politics and government--19th Century
- Series I. Correspondence
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I comprises the bulk of the surviving personal and professional correspondence of the great experimental chemist, Robert Hare. Though weak in documenting Hare's early career, the correspondence provides some key insights into his work from the early 1820s through mid-1840s, and more importantly, fleshes out the intellectual context in which Hare operated. The material from the 1790s is related to the business activities of the merchant and politician John Innis Clark of Providence, Rhode Island. (John Innis and Lydia Clark were Robert Hare’s in-laws.) The collection also contains facsimiles of various papers by George and Martha Washington, Benedict Arnold, Wythe, and Major Andre (various dates; B H22 no.1); an account book kept by Hare and his wife (180 pp., 1806-1829; B H22 no.3) and a volume by Hare on cyclones (ca. 60 pp., n.d.; B H22 no.4). With the exception of the letters by Uylenbroek (in Latin), Senturner (in German), Dr Gregory (in French), E. Durand, Translation of experiment (in French), APS Meeting extract January 1842 (in French), Robert Hare to Arago (in French), and the undated essay on tornadoes (in French), the material is in English. A typed table of contents is included in the box.
  Most of the material relates to Hare’s interest in chemistry, including the work he conducted while a professor at the University of Pennsylvania from 1818 to 1847. Benjamin Silliman recommended Hare for the chair in chemistry in the medical school that had been vacated by the death of Dr. Barton in 1815 (28 December 1815), but Hare was not appointed to a faculty position until several years later. Hare calculated the average income of a professor of chemistry at the university to be $4,560 (Account of students…, 1827-1832). A few letters refer to Hare’s disagreement with the University of Pennsylvania over structures he had allegedly erected without proper authorization on university property (February to 1846). Hare resigned his professorship in Chemistry in 1847, a decision that William Rush, a former pupil, regretted (17 May 1847). Hare’s donation of his apparatus to the Smithsonian is discussed in his letters with Joseph Henry in the 1850s.
  An item that illuminates Hare’s work outside of academia is the letter to the mayor of New York, in which Hare explains in detail how he plans to “undertake to reform the management and disposal of the offal of animals which die naturally or are slaughtered within the City of New York” (20 November 1850). An undated essay deals with the prevention of animal carcasses from becoming a nuisance.
  Several items relate to the activities of Robert Hare and his father during a visit to London in the spring of 1841. For example, the collection includes a number of tickets to various events – from lectures at the Royal Institution and the Athenaeum to events at the British and Foreign Aborigines Protection Society, to social engagement with various individuals, including Colonel Sykes, and W. H. Guillemard.
  The collection includes some material that sheds light on Hare’s activities outside of the sciences, including reform causes, financial matters, and politics. Some of these writings were evidently submitted to various newspapers for publication. There are essays and lectures (mostly undated) on a wide variety of topics, such as credit and paper money, religion, electricity, tornadoes, slaughtering houses, Voltaire, slavery, “the Irish and the British,” and the mails and the railroads. Hare’s interests also include several charitable causes. For example, that Hare was critical of the treatment of Native Americans is evident from a letter and gift sent by Samual Webb. Webb refers to Hare’s ”eloquent appeal…on behalf of the oppressed Indians; and the manly indignation expressed” by him (29 November 1838). Hare’s sympathetic views of the hardships experienced by miners in England are reflected in his letter to Daniel Coxe. Lamenting the high accident and death rate among miners in England, Hare wonders whether it was “not probable that if the labourers had belonged to the proprietors, as our negroes belong to our planters, that more care would have been taken of their lives and limbs” (3 October 1850). Hare’s abolitionist sentiments are evident from the undated “Miscellaneous notes on slavery,” and his undated proposal to create a registry of “the African race” relates his views on the Fugitive Slave law and related issues.
  An interesting item that sheds light on Hare’s political sentiments is an essay in which he defends the wearing of black cockades in 1798 against the attacks by Samuel Breck (November 1798). Another item related to political matters in the 1790s are the resolutions adopted by “the young citizens of Philadelphia,” in which they praised “the measures pursued by the Executive of the United States, to effect a reconciliation with the Republic of France” (1 May 1798). An address to John Adams conveys these views in greater detail (May 1798). Hare’s relentless criticism of Democrats and ardent support for “Federalism” is evident from an essay on the subject he submitted for publication (To the Editors, n.d.). A critical essay on the election of Thomas Jefferson to the presidency of the APS not only points out that in Jefferson’s “notes on Virginia, there is nothing too deep for the comprehension of a child,” but also accuses Jefferson of “devotion to the weak, ignorant, deluded populace” (1800). An assortment of undated “Miscellaneous notes on political matters” includes additional writings on Federalism, the Whig party, and related topics.
  Also of interest is a badge worn in honor of Lafayette’s visit in 1824, as well as a letter by E. Campbell in which she refers to the “bustle” caused by the general’s arrival in Williamsburg (27 October 1824).
  In his later years Hare became an ardent defender of Spiritualism. Items that refer to Spiritualism include a letter by Duncan McKean in which the author discusses “new and more rational views of God and nature than heretofore known” (11 November 1856). A letter by Benjamin Silliman consists of a lengthy appeal to his old friend to abandon Spiritualism. Silliman urges Hare to “view the Christ of History as I do” and “to examine the position you have taken, a position which appears to me full of danger (May 1857). After assuring Silliman that he would carefully consider his points, he explains that he considers “pure Spiritualism and pure Christianity as one.” Moreover, he describes several sittings he recently participated in (8 June 1857). Also included in the collection is a letter in which Hare welcomes “another intelligent convert to Spiritualism” [1857], as well as an undated essay titled “Concerning Christianity.”